<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cyano on Luc Cornet</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/cyano/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cyano on Luc Cornet</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/cyano/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A constrained</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/template/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/template/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;XX&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A constrained SSU-rRNA phylogeny reveals the unsequenced diversity of photosynthetic Cyanobacteria (Oxyphotobacteria)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/ssu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/ssu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luc Cornet, Annick Wilmotte, Emmanuelle J. Javaux and Denis Baurain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Cyanobacteria are an ancient phylum of prokaryotes that contain the class Oxyphotobacteria. This group has been extensively studied by phylogenomics notably because it is widely accepted that Cyanobacteria were responsible for the spread of photosynthesis to the eukaryotic domain. The aim of this study was to evaluate the fraction of the oxyphotobacterial diversity for which sequenced genomes are available for genomic studies. For this, we built a phylogenomic-constrained SSU rRNA (16S) tree to pinpoint unexploited clusters of Oxyphotobacteria that should be targeted for future genome sequencing, so as to improve our understanding of Oxyphotobacteria evolution.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s13104-018-3543-y&#34;&gt;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s13104-018-3543-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Consensus assessment of the contamination level of publicly available cyanobacterial genomes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/conta1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/conta1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luc Cornet, Loïc Meunier, Mick Van Vlierberghe, Raphaël R. Léonard, Benoit Durieu, Yannick Lara, Agnieszka Misztak, Damien Sirjacobs, Emmanuelle J. Javaux, Hervé Philippe, Annick Wilmotte, Denis Baurain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Publicly available genomes are crucial for phylogenetic and metagenomic studies, in which contaminating sequences can be the cause of major problems. This issue is expected to be especially important for Cyanobacteria because axenic strains are notoriously difficult to obtain and keep in culture. Yet, despite their great scientific interest, no data are currently available concerning the quality of publicly available cyanobacterial genomes. As reliably detecting contaminants is a complex task, we designed a pipeline combining six methods in a consensus strategy to assess the contamination level of 440 genome assemblies of Cyanobacteria. Two methods are based on published reference databases of ribosomal genes (SSU rRNA 16S and ribosomal proteins), one is indirectly based on a reference database of marker genes (CheckM), and three are based on complete genome analysis. Among those genome-wide methods, Kraken and DIAMOND blastx share the same reference database that we derived from Ensembl Bacteria, whereas CONCOCT does not require any reference database, instead relying on differences in DNA tetramer frequencies. Given that all the six methods appear to have their own strengths and limitations, we used the consensus of their rankings to infer that &amp;gt;5% of cyanobacterial genome assemblies are highly contaminated by foreign DNA (i.e., contaminants were detected by 5 or 6 methods). Our results will help researchers to check the quality of publicly available genomic data before use in their own analyses. Moreover, we argue that journals should make mandatory the submission of raw read data along with genome assemblies in order to facilitate the detection of contaminants in sequence databases.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0200323&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0200323&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cyanobacteria evolution: Insight from the fossil record</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/fossil/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/fossil/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Catherine F. Demoulin, Yannick J. Lara, Luc Cornet, Camille François, Denis Baurain, Annick Wilmotte, Emmanuelle J. Javaux&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Cyanobacteria played an important role in the evolution of Early Earth and the biosphere. They are responsible for the oxygenation of the atmosphere and oceans since the Great Oxidation Event around 2.4 Ga, debatably earlier. They are also major primary producers in past and present oceans, and the ancestors of the chloroplast. Nevertheless, the identification of cyanobacteria in the early fossil record remains ambiguous because the morphological criteria commonly used are not always reliable for microfossil interpretation. Recently, new biosignatures specific to cyanobacteria were proposed. Here, we review the classic and new cyanobacterial biosignatures. We also assess the reliability of the previously described cyanobacteria fossil record and the challenges of molecular approaches on modern cyanobacteria. Finally, we suggest possible new calibration points for molecular clocks, and strategies to improve our understanding of the timing and pattern of the evolution of cyanobacteria and oxygenic photosynthesis.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2019.05.007&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2019.05.007&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Draft Genome Sequence of the Axenic Strain Phormidesmispriestleyi ULC007, a Cyanobacterium Isolated from Lake Bruehwiler (Larsemann Hills, Antarctica)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/ulc007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/ulc007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yannick Lara, Benoit Durieu, Luc Cornet, Olivier Verlaine, Rosmarie Rippka, Igor S. Pessi, Agnieszka Misztak, Bernard Joris, Emmanuelle J. Javaux, Denis Baurain, Annick Wilmotte&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Phormidesmis priestleyi ULC007 is an Antarctic freshwater cyanobacterium. Its draft genome is 5,684,389 bp long. It contains a total of 5,604 protein-encoding genes, of which 22.2% have no clear homologues in known genomes. To date, this draft genome is the first one ever determined for an axenic cyanobacterium from Antarctica.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1128/genomea.01546-16&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1128/genomea.01546-16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metagenomic assembly of new (sub)polar Cyanobacteria and their associated microbiome from non-axenic cultures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/cyanometa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/cyanometa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luc Cornet, Amandine R. Bertrand, Marc Hanikenne​, Emmanuelle J. Javaux, Annick Wilmotte​ and Denis Baurain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Cyanobacteria form one of the most diversified phyla of Bacteria. They are important ecologically as primary producers, for Earth evolution and biotechnological applications. Yet, Cyanobacteria are notably difficult to purify and grow axenically, and most strains in culture collections contain heterotrophic bacteria that were probably associated with Cyanobacteria in the environment. Obtaining cyanobacterial DNA without contaminant sequences is thus a challenging and time-consuming task. Here, we describe a metagenomic pipeline that enables the easy recovery of genomes from non-axenic cultures. We tested this pipeline on 17 cyanobacterial cultures from the BCCM/ULC public collection and generated novel genome sequences for 12 polar or subpolar strains and three temperate ones, including three early-branching organisms that will be useful for phylogenomics. In parallel, we assembled 31 co-cultivated bacteria (12 nearly complete) from the same cultures and showed that they mostly belong to Bacteroidetes and Proteobacteria, some of them being very closely related in spite of geographically distant sampling sites.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1099/mgen.0.000212&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1099/mgen.0.000212&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ORPER: A Workflow for Constrained SSU rRNA Phylogenies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/orper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/orper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luc Cornet, Anne-Catherine Ahn, Annick Wilmotte, and Denis Baurain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;he continuous increase in sequenced genomes in public repositories makes the choice of interesting bacterial strains for future sequencing projects ever more complicated, as it is difficult to estimate the redundancy between these strains and the already available genomes. Therefore, we developed the Nextflow workflow “ORPER”, for “ORganism PlacER”, containerized in Singularity, which allows the determination the phylogenetic position of a collection of organisms in the genomic landscape. ORPER constrains the phylogenetic placement of SSU (16S) rRNA sequences in a multilocus reference tree based on ribosomal protein genes extracted from public genomes. We demonstrate the utility of ORPER on the Cyanobacteria phylum, by placing 152 strains of the BCCM/ULC collection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
