<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fungi on Luc Cornet</title>
    <link>https://lcornet.github.io/tags/fungi/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fungi on Luc Cornet</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://lcornet.github.io/tags/fungi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>AMAW: automated gene annotation for non-model eukaryotic genomes</title>
      <link>https://lcornet.github.io/publications/amaw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcornet.github.io/publications/amaw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loïc Meunier, Denis Baurain, Luc Cornet&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;&#xA;Background: The annotation of genomes is a crucial step regarding the analysis of new genomic data and resulting insights, and this especially for emerging organisms which allow researchers to access unexplored lineages, so as to expand our knowledge of poorly represented taxonomic groups. Complete pipelines for eukaryotic genome annotation have been proposed for more than a decade, but the issue is still challenging. One of the most widely used tools in the field is MAKER2, an annotation pipeline using experimental evidence (mRNA-seq and proteins) and combining different gene prediction tools. MAKER2 enables individual laboratories and small-scale projects to annotate non-model organisms for which pre-existing gene models are not available. The optimal use of MAKER2 requires gathering evidence data (by searching and assembling transcripts, and/or collecting homologous proteins from related organisms), elaborating the best annotation strategy (training of gene models) and efficiently orchestrating the different steps of the software in a grid computing environment, which is tedious, time-consuming and requires a great deal of bioinformatic skills.&#xA;Methods: To address these issues, we present AMAW (Automated MAKER2 Annotation Wrapper), a wrapper pipeline for MAKER2 that automates the above-mentioned tasks. Importantly, AMAW also exists as a Singularity container recipe easy to deploy on a grid computer, thereby overcoming the tricky installation of MAKER2.&#xA;Use case: The performance of AMAW is illustrated through the annotation of a selection of 32 protist genomes, for which we compared its annotations with those produced with gene models directly available in AUGUSTUS.&#xA;Conclusions: Importantly, AMAW also exists as a Singularity container recipe easy to deploy on a grid computer, thereby overcoming the tricky installation of MAKER2.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://f1000research.com/articles/12-186&#34;&gt;https://f1000research.com/articles/12-186&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The taxonomy of the Trichophyton rubrum complex: a phylogenomic approach</title>
      <link>https://lcornet.github.io/publications/trico/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcornet.github.io/publications/trico/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luc Cornet​, Elizabet D&amp;rsquo;hooge, Nicolas Magain, Dirk Stubbe​, Ann Packeu, Denis Baurain, and Pierre Becker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The medically relevant Trichophyton rubrum species complex has a variety of phenotypic presentations but shows relatively little genetic differences. Conventional barcodes, such as the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) region or the beta-tubulin gene, are not able to completely resolve the relationships between these closely related taxa. T. rubrum, T. soudanense and T. violaceum are currently accepted as separate species. However, the status of certain variants, including the T. rubrum morphotypes megninii and kuryangei and the T. violaceum morphotype yaoundei, remains to be deciphered. We conducted the first phylogenomic analysis of the T. rubrum species complex by studying 3105 core genes of 18 new strains from the BCCM/IHEM culture collection and nine publicly available genomes. Our analyses revealed a highly resolved phylogenomic tree with six separate clades. Trichophyton rubrum, T. violaceum and T. soudanense were confirmed in their status of species. The morphotypes T. megninii, T. kuryangei and T. yaoundei all grouped in their own respective clade with high support, suggesting that these morphotypes should be reinstituted to the species-level. Robinson-Foulds distance analyses showed that a combination of two markers (a ubiquitin-protein transferase and a MYB DNA-binding domain-containing protein) can mirror the phylogeny obtained using genomic data, and thus represent potential new markers to accurately distinguish the species belonging to the T. rubrum complex.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1099/mgen.0.000707&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1099/mgen.0.000707&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The unusual Gasteromycetes Lycogalopsis solmsii belongs to the gomphoid-phalloid group.</title>
      <link>https://lcornet.github.io/publications/vincent/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lcornet.github.io/publications/vincent/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VINCENT DEMOULIN, LUC CORNET, EMILIE DELBRUYÈRE and DENIS BAURAIN&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;The rare tropical Gasteromycetes Lycogalopsis solmsii has been found twice at thirty years interval in the Singapore Botanic Gardens. From the most recent find a culture could be isolated, which allowed DNA extraction and sequencing of about 2000 bp from the nuclear ribosomal DNA. Comparison to a large sample of Basidiomycetes was only possible for a part of the large ribosomal subunit, but clearly indicated affiliation to the gomphoid-phalloid group, without any relationship to Lycoperdales or Agaricales, as stated in the Dictionary of the Fungi.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orbi.uliege.be/bitstream/2268/151465/1/Demoulin_et_al_2013_Acta_Mycologica_postprint_editor.pdf&#34;&gt;https://orbi.uliege.be/bitstream/2268/151465/1/Demoulin_et_al_2013_Acta_Mycologica_postprint_editor.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
